So another responsibility of the board of course
is ensuring compliance and adequate internal control.
Compliance in this regard speaks to compliance with
regulations.
There's a lot of scrutiny by regulators of
ensuring that the board recognises its own responsibility
in this regard and it's not enough to
say that oh we don't know we've left
it to management.
Management is the one that should ensure compliance
with regulations with the provisions of our licence
for instance bank or other regulated entity.
The board has to emplace a structure that
ensures that not only do we understand or
know what regulations govern the entity or the
industry that we're operating in but that the
board has a way of getting reports periodically
on the level of compliance.
The board also has to establish ethical leadership
and this is done by ensuring that there's
a code of ethics which is well understood
and disseminated across the organisation and also ensuring
that there's a whistleblowing policy that provides an
avenue for people to report infractions of the
code.
Another major responsibility of the board is that
of transparency and disclosure and this is around
financial disclosures.
So the financial statements at every given point
in time are expected to reflect a true
and fair view of the business and information
has to be provided equally timely and accurately
to all stakeholders.
Directors are not expected to take undue advantage
of their position as directors and use information
relating to the financial performance of the company
to their own advantage and for example let's
say it's a quoted company that is about
to declare dividend and that information is not
known to members of the public.
Directors are not expected to take advantage of
that information themselves and then begin to pile
up the shares of the company ahead of
disclosing that decision to declare a dividend to
the public.
So in that regard there are typically closed
periods where the shares of the business are
not traded when the information has not been
made available to other members of the public
just to ensure that there is equity and
fairness in dealing with the shares of the
company.
So having discussed the duties and responsibilities, most
of these duties are statutory as you would
recall they're from the Companies and Allied Matters
Act and so if they are statutory duties
it means that there are consequences for breach.
Some of the consequences of course are reputational
and they might not necessarily have statutory consequences.
I mean damage to reputation to a lot
of directors is even more important than other
consequences.
There's personal liability I had mentioned earlier on
that if directors abuse their power they can
be personally liable for losses to the business.
There's imprisonment as you will see in the
material that is available and attached to this
video.
You will see that we have had cases
in Nigeria of directors that have been imprisoned
for breaching their duties as directors.
They can be fined and sued for losses
so they can be removed from office.
Another karma 2020, remover from office is a
disqualification for life for a director for an
individual.
Once you are removed from office following the
procedure under karma you cannot be appointed as
a director ever again and of course they
can be disqualified from holding the position of
a director.